<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech or confession of Sir Alexander Carew Baronet: who was beheaded on Tower-hill on Munday Decemb. 23. 1644. Published by authority.</title>
            <author>Carew, Alexander, Sir, 1609-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C543</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E22_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865355</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865355</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80198)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 4:E22[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech or confession of Sir Alexander Carew Baronet: who was beheaded on Tower-hill on Munday Decemb. 23. 1644. Published by authority.</title>
                  <author>Carew, Alexander, Sir, 1609-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Bates at the Maiden-head on Snow-hill, neere the Conduit. And J.W.J. in the Old-baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Carew, Alexander, --  Sir, 1609-1644.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPEECH OR CONFESSION OF Sir Alexander Carew BARONET: Who was beheaded on Tower-hill on Munday <hi>Decemb.</hi> 23. 1644.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Bates</hi> at the Maiden-head on Snow-hill, neere the Conduit. And <hi>J.W.J.</hi> in the Old-baily. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:117595:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117595:2"/>
            <head>The Speech or Confeſsion of Sir <hi>Alexander Carew</hi> Baronet, who was beheaded on Tower-hill, on Munday <hi>Decemb.</hi> 23. 1644.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N Munday <hi>December</hi> 23. in the forenoone about 10. of the Clocke, Sir <hi>Alexander Carew</hi> was brought from the Tower, guarded by the Lieutenant thereof, and his Officers (aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by two Companies of the Trained-Bands) unto a Scaffold erected on Tower-Hill for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>After he was come upon the Scaffold he ſpake to the Miniſters that were with him, and one Miniſter deſired him to ſpeak ſomewhat to clear the Juſtice againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ca.</hi> The greateſt enemy againſt me under
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117595:3"/>the Sun can lay but the ſuſpition of the fact a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me; I deſire not to ſpin out time, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be at my period, I have beſought God on my knees oftentimes that I might be diſſolved, and God would never grant it me till now, and bleſſed be God for it.</p>
            <p>Min. <hi>We may not deſire to goe out of the World, but upon a true foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ca.</hi> God knowes his own, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Lieut. <hi>When you went downe into Cornewell, theſe were your words, you bid me, God be with me, and hoped you ſhould give a good account of your bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ca.</hi> I'le lay no blame upon any other body, but take all to my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Min. <hi>You ſay the onely true way to ſalvation is by Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ca.</hi> I confeſſe it, and I confeſſe my wayes, that I am a ſinfull creature to God, with all my heart, I acknowledge it before God and all you.</p>
            <p>Min. <hi>Thinke not that hee will ſtraine your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ca.</hi> No, God forbid, but ile doe that duty vvhich I come here for, I thanke you all for your good admonitions, and it is not now to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117595:3"/>do, for I have ſurvayed my ſelfe over and over againe, and with indignation for my ſinnes, and eſpecially my Pride, and my ſtout hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Min. <hi>It is ſtoutneſſe that ſhould trouble us all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ca.</hi> All that you can lay to my charge is but intention, and no man knowes my intentions better then my ſelfe, and they ſhall die with my ſelfe, put me to what Tortures you pleaſe; Sir, this is cleare that vvhen I came a ſhore at Plimouth, I asked them whether they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me what I ſaid, they told me no. I am in that condition that whatſoever I ſay is not to be believed, and therefore I have leave to hold my peace.</p>
            <p>Then being demanded, whom he would have ſtay with him on the Scaffold, he turned to his brethren, and ſaid, Theſe are my kindred, my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors were counted honeſt men.</p>
            <p>The people calling, and deſiring to ſee him, room was made for him to come to the front of the Scaffold, where he ſpake thus to the people:</p>
            <p>GEntlemen, I hope you'l (in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of my weake body) not expect that I ſhould ſpeake much to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117595:4"/>you, neither is it my part to diſcourſe (nor my deſire) of my owne actions, and to juſtifie my ſelfe, but I ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confeſſe as the poore Publican did, <hi>Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire your prayers to God for me, and I pray to God for you, that no one drop of my blood may be required at any mans hands. I forgive all the world, with as full and hearty deſire as mortall man can, and I beſeech God to forgive me mine. The God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, that ſeeth, heareth, and beholdeth, knowes that I lie not. I have deſired with unfained deſire and hearty affection to be diſſolved and to be with Chriſt, knowing it ſhall be better for me, being aſſured thereby to be freed from the miſery of ſinne, and enter into a better life. It was the laſt words and writing of my grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117595:4"/>and here of my father,
<note place="margin">Holding forth a little Book.</note> the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their eternall peace and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, after the diſſolution of this body of theirs, in which they lived here on earth; it is mine likewiſe. I have no more to ſay, but I take my humble leave of you.</p>
            <p>Then he deſired the people to joyne with him in ſinging the 23 Pſalm, which he tuned, and read himſelfe to the people. The laſt words of the Pſalm being ended, he added,</p>
            <p>And God aſsiſting me, ſeale my vow with my blood, and rather ſuffer wrong then doe it.</p>
            <p>Then the Executioner ſpake to him deſiring him to forgive him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ca.</hi> I forgive thee and thanke thee too with Heart unfained, and give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him money ſaid, prethee leave my Clothes take my Head, and doe it handſomely elſe thou canſt not ſpeak Dutch, and ſay <hi>wel godon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117595:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>J</hi> die <hi>J</hi> thanke God rich in Gods favour.</p>
            <p>Then bidding his friends God be vvith you he ſpake to the Executioner.</p>
            <p>Doeſt thou heare, when <hi>I</hi> ſay, Lord though thou killeſt me yet will <hi>J</hi> put my truſt in thee, then doe thou cut off my head, For it was the laſt words that ever my Mother ſpoke when ſhee died.</p>
            <p>And when hee had ſaid Lord into thy hands <hi>J</hi> commend my ſpirit, hee layd himſelfe downe, with his Head over the Blocke and ſpeaking theſe words, Lord though, &amp;c. And then the Executioner did his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
